听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
大家好 我叫Martin Kleppmann
Hello, everybody, my name is Martin Kleppmann.
我将在接下来的8节课中为大家讲解分布式系统
And I'm going to be giving the next 8 lectures on distributed systems.
这是“并发与分布式系统”课程后半部分的内容
This is the second half of the course on Concurrent and Distributed Systems.
在课程的前半部分
And so, in the first half of this course,
大家已经学习了很多单一进程中的并发方法
you've seen a lot on concurrency that occurs within a single process.
特别是当单一进程中包含多个线程时
So, especially when you have multiple threads within a single process
多个线程将会并发执行
that are performing operation concurrently,
面对这一场景 大家已经学习了如何解决互斥问题
you have seen how to deal with mutual exclusion, for example,
学习了多种保证并发安全的算法
and various algorithms for ensuring safe concurrency.
在此类并发系统中
Now, in this kind of concurrent system,
所有的线程通常共享单一的地址空间
you have all of the threads usually sharing a single address space.
因此 你可以直接将一个变量从一个线程传递到另一个线程
And so, you can just pass a variable from one thread to another thread,
这个变量可以是指针 也可以是任何对象的引用
and that variable can contain pointers or references to arbitrary objects.
这当然可以做到 因为单个线程可以访问的内存地址
And this will work, because the memory addresses that one thread can access
与其他线程可以访问的内存地址是相同的
are the same as the memory addresses that another thread can access.
现在 当我们切换到分布式系统后 情况就变了
Now, when we move to distributed systems, this changes.
在分布式系统中 我们仍然要面对并发问题
So, in distributed systems, we still have concurrency.
我们仍然需要执行多个进程和多个线程
We still have multiple processes and multiple threads
每个进程和线程都在并发处理任务
performing operations concurrently potentially.
但我们还需要面对一个额外的挑战
But we also have the additional challenge that
现在我们讨论的不再是单台计算机上运行单个程序了
now we're talking about not just a single program running on a single computer,
而是多台计算机上运行多个程序
but multiple programs running on multiple computers
而多台计算机需要通过网络实现通信
where those computers are communicating via a network.
在系统中引入网络
And this aspect that we are now introducing this network
是分布式系统是分布式的重要原因
is part of what makes a distributed system distributed.
分布式系统的另一个特征是 我们不再分享单一的地址空间了
Another aspect is also that we don't have a single shared address space anymore.
指针在单进程下是有意义的
So, a pointer that makes sense in one process.
但如果你通过网络把指针发送给运行在另一台计算机上的另一个进程时
If you send it over the network to another process running on a different computer,
这个指针对于消息的接收方来说一般就没有任何意义了
that pointer will not necessarily make any sense to the recipient of that message.
因此 我们需要考虑使用其他的方法
And so, we have to think about different ways of
使并发实体间能够分享数据
sharing data between these concurrent entities.
我们来看看分布式系统的定义
So, a definition of a distributed system,
Leslie Lamport给出了一个玩笑般的定义
small joking definition provided by Leslie Lamport is that
分布式系统是指
a distributed system is a system in which
你甚至可能都觉得不存在的一个计算机错误
the failure of a computer you didn't even know existed
就能导致计算机不可用的一个系统
can render your own computer unusable.
这是一个好的定义吗？每个人都会有不同的意见
Whether this is a good definition or not? We can debate.
不过Leslie Lamport可是分布式系统领域的一位传奇人物
But Leslie Lamport is a bit of a legend in the area of distributed systems.
我们将会学习到很多他在几十年前就完成的工作
And we will see various aspects of work that he's done over the decades.
当然 很多人都为这个领域做出了突出的贡献
And of course, lots of other people have done work in this area.
我们在课程中也将讲到其他人的工作
And we will see that over the course of these lectures.
更一般地 我认为我们可以把分布式系统定义为
So, more generally, I think I would define a distributed system as one in which
你有多台计算机或多台计算设备
you have got multiple computers or computing devices.
这些设备可能是智能手机
These devices might be smartphones.
可能是机器人
They might be robots.
可能是自动驾驶车辆
They might be self-driving cars.
可能是桌面计算机
They might be desktop computers.
可能是数据中心的服务器
They might be servers in the data center.
可以是任意一类计算设备
So, any sort of computing device really.
这些计算设备通过某种网络实现通信
And these computing devices are communicating by some kind of network,
这里的网络可以是互联网
which might be the Internet.
这些计算设备尝试共同完成某项任务
And they are trying to achieve some kind of task together.
研究分布式系统 就是在研究
And the study of distributed systems is really the study of
如何让这些不同的计算设备协作
how do we coordinate the activities of these different devices
使它们可以共同完成某项任务
in such a way that they achieve together the task that they are trying to achieve.
我需要先介绍一些背景信息
So, I will start with a little bit of background.
首先是课程本身的相关信息
First, just the administrative things to get that done.
第一 你可能想阅读本课程的其他相关资料
So, first of all, if you want any further background reading on this course,
当然了 讲义本身的内容是自包含的
hopefully, the lecture notes will be reasonably self-contained,
不过如果你感兴趣的话 也可以阅读相关书籍 学习更多细节
but of course, further detail is available in books if you are interested.
我这里列举了很多不同风格的书籍
There are several different styles of books that I've put here on the list.
van Stenn和Tanenbaum撰写的教材是一本全面的综述类教材
So, the textbook by van Stenn and Tanenbaum is a sort of systems level overview.
他们站在应用的视角
So, it comes at distributed systems
以实际系统和实际用户的角度出发介绍分布式系统
from quite an applied angle of real applications that real people use,
本书讨论了分布式系统的原理 并讨论了分布式系统的很多实现细节
and discusses how this work, and discusses the various implementation details of it.
与其他书相比 这本书没有涉及过多的理论
It doesn't go as far into the theory as some of the other books,
这是一本面向实际应用的教材
but it's more practically oriented.
如果你喜欢理论的话 阅读列表中的第二本书是个不错的选择
If you like the theory, then the second book on this list is a good choice.
Cachi、Guerraoui和Rodrigues撰写的教材非常棒
So, the textbook by Cachi, Guerraoui, and Rodrigues is an excellent
这本书全面介绍了分布式系统的理论
but quite detailed overview of distributed systems theory.
这本书要比我在课程中讲解的内容更深
So, it goes into a lot more depth than we have time to talk about in this course.
如果你希望学习更多的理论知识 阅读这本优秀的教材就对了
But if you want to read more about the theory, this is an excellent book.
我也为此领域撰写了一本书 叫《数据密集型应用系统设计》
I also wrote a book in this area called “Designing Data Intensive Applications”.
这本书主要介绍的是分布式数据库系统
This book is a bit more oriented towards distributed database systems.
这并不是介绍广义分布式系统的书籍
So, it's not just distributed systems in general.
这本书会介绍很多数据库的相关知识
There's a lot of the other databases content in there.
这本书的受众群体是工业级软件工程师
And this book is more oriented towards industrial software engineers.
专门从事分布式数据库相关工作的工程师
So, people who are working professionally with distributed databases
可能会觉得这本书更值得一读
will probably find this kind of book useful.
最后是Bacon和Harris撰写的教材
And finally, there's the Bacon and Harris textbook,
本课程的并发系统部分已经推荐过这本书了
which was already recommended for the concurrent systems part of this course,
这本书在操作系统和分布式系统之间建立了一个连接
which really provides the link between operating systems and distributed systems.
本课程与剑桥大学很多本科的其他课程都有千丝万缕的联系
OK, so, this course is also connected to various other courses in the tripos,
很显然 并发系统也是本课程的一部分
Most obviously, concurrent systems that this course is part of.
大家去年上过的操作系统课程也与本课程相关
Also, operating systems which you studied last year.
所有操作系统相关的背景知识
So, all of the background that you had there
进程、进程间通信、进程调度等
on processes and inter-process communication and scheduling of processes,
这些背景知识都与本课程的内容相关
all of that stuff is relevant for this course.
数据库课程也与分布式系统课程相关
Also, the databases course is connected to distributed systems
我前面也提到
because as I mentioned just now,
很多现代数据库系统事实上也是分布式系统
many modern databases are in fact distributed.
这些分布式系统也会使用很多我们将在本课程介绍的技术
And they use a lot of the techniques that we will talk about in this course.
使用现代数据库时也会涉及到如何使用分布式系统
And so, using modern databases often involves using distributed systems as well.
分布式系统与计算机网络有很强的关联性
There's a strong connection between distributed systems and computer networking,
我前面说过 分布式系统一般都会涉及网络通信
because as I said, distributed systems involve network communication generally.
这两个课程的区别如下
The difference between the two courses is that
计算机网络课程主要解决的问题是
the computer networking course is mostly about
如何通过导线从一个设备向另一个设备发送字节信息
how do you actually get the bytes over the wire from one device to the other device.
主要讲解的是设备间通信的网络协议是什么样子的
So, what do the network protocols look like that enable devices to communicate.
分布式系统是基于计算机网络构造的
And then, distributed systems build on top of computer networking,
分布式系统称 假设我们已经有了设备间的通信机制
and saying, OK, assuming we now have this mechanism for devices to communicate,
我们如何保证这些设备可以按照我们期望的方式执行任务
how can we now ensure that these devices behave in the ways that we want.
本课程也与Java有联系
There's connection to further Java.
本课程会包含分布式计算的一些编程练习
So, there's programming exercises that involve a bit of distributed computing.
分布式系统的安全问题也很有趣
The security aspects of distributed systems are very interesting.
复活节学期的一门课程将会重点讲解安全方面的内容
And they are covered in a course in Easter term that's dedicated just a topic of security.
最后 下一年度的云计算课程建立在分布式系统课程所学的内容之上
And finally, next year's cloud computing course builds upon distributed systems,
因为云计算主要面对的问题是
because cloud computing is all about
如何让分布式系统灵活地处理大规模的数据
being able to flexibly process large amounts of data.
如果你有足够大量的数据
And if you have sufficiently large amounts of data,
你一般需要一个分布式系统来处理这些数据
you generally need a distributed system in order to process it.
我已经对分布式系统给出了一个简单的定义
OK, so, I gave a brief definition of what a distributed system is.
下一个问题是为什么
The next question is then why,
为什么我们要投入那么多的精力 非要让系统变成分布式的？
like why should we go to all of this effort of making a system distributed?
为什么我们不能让事情保持简单化 就用单台计算机完成任务呢？
Why can't we just use a single computer and keep things simple?
其中一个原因是 有些应用本身就是分布式的
And well, one reason is that some applications,
有些你希望计算机处理的任务本身就是分布式的
some types of things you want to do computers are inherently distributed.
如果你想用你的手机向你朋友的手机发送一条消息
So, if you want to send a message from your phone to your friend's phone,
这就不可避免地涉及到两个手机和网络通信
this inevitably involves two different phones and a network.
这就是一个分布式系统
So, this is a distributed system.
我们没办法让这个任务单机化
There's no way around it.
我们无法构造一个非分布式的消息通信系统
There's no way of building a messaging system that is not distributed
因为消息通信系统的目的就是让不同设备可以通信
if you want to be able to communicate across different devices.
构造这类软件系统
And so, building this type of software
是我们对分布式系统感兴趣的其中一个原因
is one reason why we might be interested in distributed systems.
但还有研究分布式系统的其他原因
But there are many other reasons as well.
另一个让我们对分布式系统感兴趣的原因是
So, another good reason for being interested in distributed systems is that
分布式系统会使我们的系统变得更可靠
it actually allows us to make systems more reliable.
系统变得更可靠的原因是 你现在有多台计算机
And the reason for this is, say, you have multiple computers
每台计算机都在执行某项工作
which are each performing part of some job.
如果其中一台计算机出故障了
If one of those fails,
例如其中一台计算机被重启了
maybe one of them has to be rebooted, for example,
或者其中一台计算机出现了硬件故障
or one of them has a hardware failure,
此时 剩余的计算机或许可能可以承接故障计算机的任务
then maybe the remaining computers can take over the work from the failed computer.
即使一台参与任务执行的计算机宕机了
And so now, this allows the system as a whole to continue functioning
从整体角度看 整个系统仍然可以提供服务
even though one of the computers involved in it has actually gone down.
我们想让系统分布式化的另一个原因是获得更好的性能
Another reason we might want to make systems distributed is for better performance.
例如 在互联网分布式系统中
So, for example, in Internet distributed systems,
用户可能来自世界各地
you might have users all around the world,
有些用户可能在英国 有些用户在美国
you might have some users in the UK, some users in the US,
有些用户在新西兰 有些用户在南美 用户可能来自世界各地
some users in New Zealand, some users in South Africa, wherever.
不同地区的物理距离可能会很远
And there are large distances between these different places.
从一个地区到另一个地区的网络通信速度可能比较慢
And so, network communication from one of these places to the others
消息通信可能得多花点时间
is always going to take a little while.
各个地区的通信时间至少为100毫秒
You're talking at least 100 milliseconds
因为通信时间
simply because of the speed of light
不可能超过光从一个地区到另一个地区的传播时间
that it takes for communication to travel from one continent to another.
因此 人们对分布式系统感兴趣的一个原因是
And so, one reason why people are interested in distributed systems is
把距离相近用户的数据放得更近 使系统性能变得更好
to make systems faster by putting data closer to where the people are.
如果系统的用户来自多个不同的大洲
So, if you have some users in multiple different continents,
你可以在多个不同的大洲放置计算机
you can have computers in multiple different continents.
如果每个用户都能与离他更近的计算机通信
And if you have each user communicating with the computer that is most local to them,
系统就可以避免长距离的跨洲通信
then you avoid the long-distance intercontinental communication
用户就不需要忍受跨洲通信带来的额外通信时延了
as part of the delays that are added to their communication.
使系统分布式化可以潜在帮助我们让系统运行得更快
So, making systems distributed allows us to make them faster potentially.
最后 人们构建分布式系统的另一个原因是
And finally, another reason why people build distributed systems is
解决规模更大的、单台计算机无法解决的问题
to solve bigger problems than they could with a single computer.
有些计算任务的计算规模是非常大的
So, some computing problems are simply very large scale.
考虑一个科学计算的例子 例如CERN（欧洲核子研究委员会）
So, think of scientific computing examples, like, for example, the CERN,
他们在瑞士有一个粒子加速器 其内部包含一个大型强子碰撞型加速装置
the particle accelerator in Switzerland that includes the Large Hadron Collider,
他们构建了一个特大规模的计算基础设施 包含上百万个CPU核
they have a vast computing infrastructure involving a million CPU cores,
天知道这个基础设施拥有多少块硬盘
and God knows how many hard disks,
他们用这样一个基础设施收集粒子加速器产生的数据
in order to just take all of the data that they're gathering from the particle accelerator
对这些数据进行处理和分析 从而完成新粒子发现等工作
and process it and analyze it and try to use this to discover new particles, for example.
这种规模的任务很难简单地应用单台计算机完成
Now, this scale of task would simply not be possible to achieve on a single computer,
因为还没有足够大的超级计算机
because there is no supercomputer that is big enough
可以承担如此海量数据的处理任务
to be able to handle these vast volumes of data.
即使对如此海量的数据进行简单的数据分析和处理
So, simply solving this problem of analyzing such large volumes of data
也需要用网络连接海量的小型计算机来实现
has to be done on a network of lots of small computers.
这些计算机需要分布式地处理相应的任务
And those computers have to distribute the work amongst them.
它们需要共同协作
And they have to work together
处理科学家希望完成的计算任务
in order to achieve the tasks that the scientists are trying to do.
这是我们希望用分布式系统解决的另一类关键问题
And so, this is really one of another key area in which we can use distributed systems.
即：用分布式系统处理更大规模的任务
It is to solve bigger problems.
使系统分布式化可以带来很多优点
Now, those are the advantages of making systems distributed.
不幸的是 使系统分布式化也会带来很多缺点
There are unfortunately some significant disadvantages as well.
大家可能已经很熟悉分布式系统最主要的一个缺点了
And the main disadvantage that you will be well familiar with is
一旦你尝试使用网络通信完成一些工作
whenever you're trying to do something over a network
网络可能会因为各种各样的原因而无法通信
that network might not be working for some reason.
每个人都可能有类似的经历 比如互联网无法连接
And so, everyone has experienced what it's like for the Internet to be down
比如Wi-Fi信号太弱
or for your Wi-Fi signal to be weak,
比如你身处某个国家的某个村落
or for you're in some rural part of the country
当你载入地图或做一些操作时
and your cellular data signal is weak,
你发现自己的手机蜂窝信号很弱
and you're trying to load a map or something like that.
每个人都有类似令人沮丧的经历
Everyone has experienced this kind of frustration before.
研究分布式系统 就是在研究如何处理这些令人沮丧的情况
And well, the study of distributed systems is all about the study of such frustrations.
只要我们建立的是一个
So, we assume whenever we are building a distributed system
涉及网络通信的分布式系统
that involves communication over a network,
我们就要假设网络不完全可靠
that networks are not perfectly reliable.
通信总有可能会出现故障
And so, it is always possible for communication to fail.
对于Wi-Fi网络 设备可能会因远离无线路由而断开
It is always possible that if it's a Wi-Fi network, you might be out of range,
对于有线网络 有些人可能把设备连接到了错误的网络端口
if it's a wired network, somebody might have unplugged the wrong cable,
任意网络都有可能出现临时性的阻塞情况
if it's any type of network, it might just be temporarily overloaded.
此时 网络可能会出现丢包现象
And so, it might be dropping messages.
甚至可能存在某个恶意攻击者 尝试在网络中实施干扰
Maybe even somebody might be maliciously trying to interfere with the network,
使网络丢包 甚至可能会使系统遭受拒绝服务攻击
and cause it to drop packets, maybe causing a denial-of-service attack, for example.
导致网络通信时常中断的原因多种多样
There are many reasons why communication might not work from time to time.
因此 我们必须构建一个足够健壮的系统
And so, we have to build systems that are robust
即使网络通信时常中断
so that even if communication is interrupted from time to time,
系统作为整体仍然可以按照正确的方式工作
the system as a whole still functions in some correct way
当然 我们可以定义何为正确的方式
where, of course, we can define what we mean with correct,
但核心是我们希望系统能够持续运行
but we want it to continue functioning.
分布式系统可能出现错误的另一种可能的情况是
Another thing that can go wrong in distributed systems is that
有些进程中运行的代码可能会崩溃
some of the processes, running the code might crash.
例如 如果你有一个包含多台计算机的系统
And for example, if you have a system consisting of multiple computers,
你重启了其中一台计算机
and you reboot one of them,
你可能希望剩余计算机仍然可以处理用户发起的请求
you probably want the remaining computers to carry on the task of serving user requests.
此时 我们希望的是 即使其中一个进程临时崩溃
And so, what we want here is that one of the processes is temporarily out of action,
整个系统仍然可以不间断地运行
and we want the system as a whole to still continue nevertheless.
最后 所有这些失败情况是否会发生都是非确定性的
And finally, all of these failures can happen non-deterministically,
也就是说 我们很难得知什么时候会出现失败情况
and, that is, we simply don't know when they happen.
失败情况不可预测 任何时候都可能发生
They could happen at any moment unpredictably.
即便如此 我们仍然必须保证软件持续运行
And we still have to ensure that the software works nevertheless.
我们全力以赴 希望让分布式系统满足所谓的容错性
So, what we often strive for in distributed systems is what is known as fault tolerance,
意思是即使一部分系统失效
which means that even if some part of the system is faulty,
一部分系统无法工作
some part of the system is not working,
整个系统仍然可以持续为用户提供服务
the system as a whole still continues providing the service to the users.
这是分布式系统所面临的主要挑战之一
And so, this is one of the main challenges in distributed systems,
即如何使分布式系统满足容错性
how do we make things in such a way that they can tolerate faults.
事实上 让系统分布式化且满足容错性是极为困难的
In fact, making things distributed and fault-tolerant is so difficult
困难到让很多分布式领域的专家认为
that a lot of people who work professionally on distributed systems think that
如果你能用单台计算机解决问题 那就用单台计算机解决
oh, well, if you can solve a problem on a single computer, it's basically easy.
因此 如果你能用单台计算机解决问题
So, if you can solve a problem on a single computer,
那你就尽可能用单台计算机解决
you'll probably have a much better time just keeping it on one computer,
不要把事情变得更复杂 不要随随便便就切换到分布式系统解决
not over complicating things, not going into a distributed system setting.
分布式系统会面临各种问题
And so, all of the problems,
使用分布式系统像打开一个包含各种问题的潘多拉宝盒
this pandora's box of problems that arise with distributed systems,
只有当必须使用分布式系统时 我们才应该尝试打开这个宝盒
well, we should try and open that only if we actually have to.
正如我前面所说
But, as we said earlier,
确实有很多原因使我们必须打开这个潘多拉宝盒
there are lots of good reasons why you might have to open that box.